Register of the Paul J. Flory Papers, 1975-1986
Hoover Institution Archives
Paul J. Flory Papers, 1975-1986
85022
Flory, Paul J.
8 manuscript boxes (3.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The collection includes correspondence, statements, memoranda, bulletins, reports, conference material, press releases, and clippings relating to the civil rights of dissident scientists in various countries, especially the Soviet Union. Much of the material concerns the cases of Andreĭ Sakharov, Yuri Orlov, and Anatoly Shcharansky.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Searchworks at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Searchworks is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Scientists For Sakharov, Orlov And Shcharansky Records, Hoover Institution Archives
Paul J. Flory Papers, Chemical Heritage Foundation
Biographical Note
1910 June 19 Born, Sterling, Illinois
1931 Bachelor's degree, Manchester College
1934 Ph.D in Chemistry, Ohio State University
1936 Married Emily Catherine Tabor
1937-1939 Employed at Basic Science Research Laboratory of the University of Cincinnati
1940-1943 Employed at Esso Laboratories of the Standard Oil Development Company (later known as Exxon)
1943-1948 Employed at the Research Laboratory of the Goodyear Tire and Rubber Company
1948 Accepted professorship, Cornell University
1961-1975 Professor of Chemistry, Stanford University
1974 Nobel Laureate (Chemistry)
1975 Awarded National Medal of Science
1978 Withdrew from a symposium in Tashkent in response to persecution of Soviet scientists
1980 Delegate, Hamburg Scientific Forum, Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe (CSCE)
1982 Panelist, Madrid CSCE
1984 Served as spokesman for a group of scholars offering themselves as personal witnesses with the hope of securing medical treatment for Elena Bonner
1985 Co-authored public letter to the editor of Science concerning National Academy of Science (NAS) scientific exchange protocol
1985 Died
Sources: Nobelprize.org
http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/chemistry/laureates/1974/flory-autobio.html
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection includes correspondence, statements, memoranda, bulletins, reports, conference material, press releases, and clippings relating to the civil rights of dissident scientists in various countries, especially the Soviet Union. Much of the material concerns the cases of Andreĭ Sakharov, Yuri Orlov, and Anatoly Shcharansky.
These papers document Paul J. Flory's involvement in various civil rights organizations concerned with the treatment of dissident scientists. They include materials from organizations such as Scientists for Sakharov, Orlov and Shcharansky (SOS), Helsinki Watch, National Academy of Sciences (NAS) Committee on Human Rights, Andrei Sakharov Institute, and the Committee of Concerned Scientists, Inc. These materials document the advocacy and educational work of these groups, including statements and letters supporting dissident scientists. Also included are materials on the Hamburg Scientific Forum, which was mandated by the Helsinki Final Act (also known as the Helsinki Accords) of the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe (CSCE).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
American chemist.; Civil rights.; Civil rights--Soviet Union.; Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Scientists--Soviet Union.; Sakharov, Andreĭ, 1921-; Shcharansky, Anatoly.; Orlov, Yuri, 1924-; Scientists for Sakharov, Orlov and Shcharansky.
Collection Contents
- Business cards and notes, undated (Folder 1: 1)
- Commission on Security and Cooperation in Europe, 1982, undated (Folder 1: 2)
- Committee of Concerned Scientists, Inc. (Folder 1)
  - 1978-1983 (Folder 1: 3-4)
  - 1984-1985 (Folder 1: 5)
- Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe (Box 1)
  - General, 1978-1982 (Folder 1: 6)
    Includes Madrid Conference 1980 and 1982
  - Hamburg Scientific Forum (Folder 1)
    - Agendas and briefings, 1980-1981 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Correspondence, 1979-1984 (Folder 1: 8)
    - Forum binder, 1978-1980 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Hearing on the Scientific Forum, 1978-1980 (Folder 2: 1)
    - Statements and reports, 1979-1980 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Statements and reports by Flory, 1980 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Miscellany, 1980 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Madrid, 1982 (Folder 2: 5)
- Correspondence (Folder 2)
  - General, 1980-1985 (Folder 2: 6)
  - Human rights, miscellaneous letters, 1976-1985 (Folder 2: 7)
- Frenkel, S., 1980-1984 (Folder 2: 8)
- Helsinki Watch (Folder 2)
  - 1979, 1985 (Folder 2: 9)
  - 1980 (Folder 2: 10)
  - 1980 (Folder 3: 1)
  - 1981 (Folder 3: 2)
  - 1981-1985 (Folder 3: 3)
  - 1985 (Folder 3: 4)
- Herczynski, 1982 (Folder 3: 5)
- Human rights (Folder 3)
  - General, 1978-1985 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Clippings, 1983-1984 (Folder 3: 7)
  - Organizations, Miscellaneous, 1980-1983 (Folder 3: 8)
- International Committee of Scientists for Soviet Refusniks, 1985 (Folder 3: 9)
- International Conference on Collective Phenomena (Moscow Refusnik Seminar held 1983 December), 1980-1983 (Folder 3: 10)
- Jewish organizations, 1977-1984 (Folder 3: 11)
- National Academy of Sciences (NAS) Committee on Human Rights (Folder 4)
  - General (Folder 4)
    - 1979 (Folder 4: 1)
    - 1980 (Folder 4: 2)
    - 1981 (Folder 4: 3)
    - 1982 (Folder 4: 4-5)
    - 1983 (Folder 4: 6-7)
    - 1984 (Folder 4: 8)
    - 1985 (Folder 5: 1)
  - Handler, Philip (NAS Letter to Members), 1979 (Folder 5: 2)
  - Letters supporting various oppressed scientists (Folder 5)
    - 1977-1979 (Folder 5: 3)
    - 1981 (Folder 5: 4)
  - Meeting, 1983 January-February (Folder 5: 5)
- National Academy of Sciences (NAS) scientific exchange protocol, 1985 (Folder 5: 6)
  Includes letter to the editor of Science, co-authored by Flory
- Printed matter, 1985-1986 (Folder 5: 7)
  Includes biographical article on Flory
- Sakharov, Andreĭ (Folder 5)
  - General (Folder 5)
    - 1979-1985 (Folder 5: 8-9)
    - 1980-1984 (Folder 5: 10)
  - Andreĭ Sakharov Institute, 1981, 1984-1985 (Folder 5: 11)
  - Clippings, 1980-1985 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Fifth International Sakharov Hearing, 1985 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Yankelevich, Efrem, 1985 (Folder 6: 3)
- Scientists for Sakharov, Orlov and Shcharansky (SOS) (Folder 6)
  - General (Folder 6)
    - 1978 (Folder 6: 4)
    - 1978-1982 (Folder 6: 5)
    - 1979 (Folder 6: 6-7)
    - 1980 (Folder 6: 8)
    - 1981 (Folder 6: 9-10)
    - 1982 (Folder 7: 1-2)
    - 1983 (Folder 7: 3-4)
    - 1984 (Folder 7: 5-6)
    - 1984-1985 (Folder 7: 7)
    - 1985 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Background information, publicity and other printed matter (Folder 7)
    - 1978 (Folder 7: 9)
    - 1979 (Folder 7: 10)
    - 1979 (Folder 8: 1)
- Shcharansky, Anatoly, 1982 (Folder 8: 2)
- Writings by Flory, 1980-1984 (Folder 8: 3)
- UNESCO, Committee for an Effective UNESCO, 1975-1979 (Folder 8: 4-6)
- USSR Tashkent Meeting, 1978-1979 (Folder 8: 7-8)
- Yarim-Agaev, Yuri, 1979-1980 (Folder 8: 9)
- Miscellany, 1983 (Folder 8: 10)